Soza family papers, 1892-2000 MS 436
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Soza family papers 1892-2000
Collection Number: MS 436
Soza, Edward, 1921-
Printed material and photographs, 1892-2000, (bulk 1990-1999). Bulk of collection contains correspondence, birth certificates, biographical information, photographs, and newspaper clippings on the Soza Family, Hispanic Arizona pioneers. The collection contains copies of primary materials as well as oversize materials of some maps, photographs and lithographs.
3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
None
Biographical Note
The Soza family was founded in 1746 by Jose Maria Soza I, a cavalryman in the Royal Spanish Army who was stationed at Presidio San Ignacio de Tubac in 1774 and was later transferred to the Presidio San Agustin del Tucson, with his wife, Rita Espinosa, with whom he fathered one son and three daughters.
Jose Maria So Soza II was the Civil Administrator of the Tumacacori Mission during the 1830’s and was married to Dona Gregoria Nunes. They had eight children.
Jose Maria Soza III married Solana Mendoza in the early 1850’s. Their daughter, Manuela Mendoza Sosa married Michael McKenna, a Civil War veteran, and they created the McKenna branch of the family.
The descendants of the Manuel and Calistro Sosa branch included the families of Antonio Campa Soza, Placido Campa Soza, Nicolas Campa Soza and Juan Soza. The Juan Soza branch became early settlers of Tempe, Arizona and have roots with the Hayden family. They were later joined by the Placido Sosa branch.
The Antonio Soza branch of the family has long been associated with Tucson and the San Pedro River Valley, where Antonio homesteaded and was engaged in farming and ranching.
The Soza family papers were complied by Edward Soza. Edward Soza was born in Benson, Arizona on March 24, 1921 and lived briefly at the Soza ancestral homestead ranch at Redington on the San Pedro River. In 1925 the family moved to California. After attending public schools in Wilmington, CA, Edward returned to Arizona and graduated with the first graduating Class of 1940, North Phoenix High School.
Edward graduated from Pennsylvania State College (now University) in 1946 with a BA degree and was commissioned Ensign USNR. He married his wife Phyllis in 1947 and together they had 3 children. He has published extensively on Soza family genealogy.
For further biographical information on the Soza family please see Edward Soza’s publication New world odyssey, a search for roots: the Sosa, Soza families of Arizona. Altadena: E. Soza, 1995.
This Collection is organized into 5 series.
Series I: Biographical
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Legal Documents
Series IV: Miscellaneous
Series V: Oversized Material
Printed material and photographs, 1892-2000, (bulk 1990-1999). The collection primarily consists of genealogical materials and data compiled by Edward Soza on the Soza family and related family lines. The bulk of the material is comprised of correspondence, biographical information, photographs and newspaper clippings focusing on the Soza family. The collection includes materials on the McKenna and Yanez families, among others. The collection also contains printed material including family trees, family reunions, wills and probates, census data, homestead documents and land deeds. Various photographs include individuals and buildings, such as the Tucson Sosa-Carrillo-Fremont House Museum.
Cisneros, Jose.; Soza, Edward; McKenna family.; Sosa family.; Sousa family.; Soza family.; Yanez family.; Sosa-Carrillo-Fremont House (Tucson, Ariz.).; Tucson Heritage Foundation (Ariz.); Arizona -- Genealogy.; Hispanic American families – Arizona – History
- Series 1: Biographical
  This series is arranged into three sections: family reunions, family trees, and individuals and families, the latter arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Biographical: Family reunions, 1975; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical: Family reunions, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical: Family reunions, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical: Family reunions: 1975, 1982, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical: Family reunions: Romero family reunion, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical: Family trees: Soza family (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biographical: Family trees: Yanez family (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Cuni/Sotelo families (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Greer family (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Hi Wo family (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: McKenna/Sosa family (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Michalec, Charles Frederick (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Biographical: Individuals and familes: Officer, James E. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Pacheco family (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Rodriguez, Elena Soza (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Soza, Albert, family of (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Soza, Amalia, 1975; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Biographical: Individuals and families: Soza, Baudelio (Bud) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Edward(1) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Edward(2) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Ezekeil (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Fred (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Jesus Moreno de (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Maria Petra de (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, Robert Lee (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Soza, William (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Biographical:Individuals and families: Yanez family (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Correspondence
  This series is divided into official correspondence and personal correspondence, each section arranged alphabetically by last name or organization name.
  - Correspondence: Official: Archivio General de Indias (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. Official: Arizona Historical Society (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. Official: Arizona State Land (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. Official: Bancroft Family (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. Official: Brown, Stanley C. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. Official: Capilla de San Antonio – Soza Ranch – Redington (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. Official: Diocese of Tucson/Bishop Moreno (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. Official: Family History Library – L.D.S. – Utah (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. Official: Garate, Donald (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. Official: Halpenny, Philip (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. Official: Hispanic Genealogical Society of New York (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. Official: Library of Congress (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. Official: Nixon, Richard M. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence. Official: Solliday, Scott (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence. Official: Sosa-Carrillo-Fremont Museum (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence. Official: Soza Cemetery (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence. Official: St. Ann’s Parish – Tubac, Arizona (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence. Official: Tempe Historical Museum (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence. Official: Tubac Historical Society (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence. Official: Tucson Heritage Foundation (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence. Official: Tumacacori National Historical Park (Box  3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence. Official: University of Arizona (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. Official: U.S. Geological Survey (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence. Official: Vasquez, Nadine (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence. Official: Vinson, Mark C. – Historian (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence. Official: Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Apodaca, Artemisa (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Elwood, E. H. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Fontana, B. L (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Gonzales, N. A. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Noble, Marguerite (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Soza, Edward (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Soza, Nicolas C. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence. Personal: Soza, Placido C. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series 3: Legal Documents
  This series is arranged into three sections: wills and probate, census data, and homestead documents and land deeds. Census data is arranged chronologically and the others are arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Legal documents: Wills & probate: Soza, Antonio (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Legal documents: Wills & probate: Soza, Jesus Maria de (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Legal documents: Census data: Tubac Census of 1831 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Legal documents: Census data: New Mexico/Arizona Census of 1860 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Blaisdell, Frank G., Homestead no.759 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Butler, Lemuel C. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Lynch, Francis P., Homestead no.1319 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: McKenna, Michael, Homestead no.79 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Montano, Leonides, Homestead no.1219 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Mungia, Jesus Maria, Homestead no.1625 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Antonio C., Homestead no.934 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Jose, Homestead no.2564 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Juan, Homestead no.48 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Juan, Homestead no.218 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Manuel M., Homestead no.03537 (Box  5, Folder 15)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Nicolas, Homestead no.759 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Placido, Homestead no.183 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Soza, Rosaura, Homestead no.3-03260 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Van Alstine, Anthony & family (Box  5, Folder 19)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Walters, Daniel, Homestead no.185 (Box 5, Folder  20)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Declarations of Intention to Become U.S. Citizens (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Post Offices in Arizona (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Samples of declaratory statements (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Legal documents: Homestead documents & land deeds: Misc. documents (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Series 4: Miscellaneous
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Miscellaneous: Cisneros, Jose (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous: City of Tucson Proclamation – 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous: Edward & Phyllis F. Soza Scholarship Endowment (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous: Miscellaneous Family Documents (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous: Newsclippings I (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous: Newsclippings II (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous: Newsclippings III (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous: Photograph of Sosa-Carrillo Fremont Museum – Tucson, Arizona (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous: The Settlement of the San Luis and Upper Santa Cruz River Valleys (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous: Sosa Surname Documentation (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous: Soza Surname Origin (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous: Tempe’s First Families (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous: Various Photographs (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series 5: Oversized materials
  - Certificates (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Cinseros, Jose (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Family Tree (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Maps (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 6)